All right, בוקר טוב Boker Tov everybody. בוקר טוב. Boker Tov. Okay,
today's דף Daf is
ס"ז, Samech Zayin, well today's official דף Daf is ס"ח. Samech Chet.
We start at the bottom of ס"ז עמוד א'. Samech Zayin Amud
Alef. And what we're going to be, we pick up here which
is on a whole multiple debate of the תנאים. Tannaim. We start
with the משנה, Mishnah, which is the position of רבי יוסי, Rabbi
Yose, which is that a woman who is pregnant, married to a
כהן, Kohen, the עובר Ubar sort of is אינו מאכיל, Eino Ma'akhil,
does not let her eat תרומה Terumah her husband dies. It's not
considered yet that she has a child. But it's enough to create
a problem. It's also פוסל Posel because he has a portion of
the slaves, he has a portion in the slaves, and as a
עובר Ubar cannot allow them, the slaves don't eat by virtue of
him. So let's take a look. We'll start again from the ברייתא
Baraita quoted at the bottom of ס"ז עמוד א'. Samech Zayin Amud
Alef. תנו רבנן, Tanu Rabbanan, our Rabbis taught: הניח בנים, Hiniach Banim,
if a woman left over sons and a husband, a כהן, Kohen,
and his wife was not pregnant. אלו ואלו אוכלים. Elu V'elu Okhlim.
The woman can eat and the woman's slaves can eat and the
husband's slaves can eat because there's a child, so the child entitles
the woman to eat and there's no problem for the slaves eating,
they're all owned by the heirs of the כהן. Kohen. הניח עובר,
Hiniach Ubar, if she's pregnant and no children are born yet. אלו
ואלו אין אוכלים. Elu V'elu Ein Okhlim. She can't eat by virtue
of the fetus because she can only eat if she has a
born child. And they can't eat because they're partly owned by the
fetus and therefore, or they're fully owned by the fetus depending on
if they're girls or whatever. Anyway, and therefore the fetus cannot, they
can't eat by virtue of him. הניח בנים והניח עוברת. Hiniach Banim
V'hiniach Ubarat. There are born children and she's pregnant. עבדי מלוג אוכלים,
Avdei Milug Okhlim, her servants can eat because she eats by virtue
of the born children. The pregnant child doesn't, the fetus doesn't affect
her
status. כדרך שהיא אוכלת, K'derekh Shehi Okhelet, the same way she eats.
עבדי צאן ברזל לא יאכלו, Avdei Tzon Barzel Lo Yokhlu, but his
servants, which apparently they're still his because she hasn't yet collected taken
them yet back out of the estate. So his, so the ones
he brought in the dowry which are now his servants, they don't
eat, מפני חלקו של עובר Mipnei Chelqo Shel Ubar because the עובר
Ubar has a portion in what the born sons have inherited and
therefore creates the problem. שעובר פוסל ואינו מאכיל. She'ubar Posel V'eino Ma'akhil.
He invalidates and he cannot feed. So he invalidates even the ones
the slaves that are owned by the born children, his presence makes
a problem, but he does not entitle the woman to eat, but
she can eat by virtue of the other born children. דברי רבי
יוסי, Divrei Rabbi Yose, that's what רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose said. So
that's consistent with the משנה, Mishnah, just sort of spelling it out.
רבי ישמעאל ברבי יוסי אומר, Rabbi Yishmael b'Re Rabbi Yose Omer, רבי
ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael the son of רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose says משום
אביו Mishum Aviv in the name of his father: הבת מאכילה הבן
אינו מאכיל. Ha-Bat Ma'akhila Ha-Ben Eino Ma'akhil. The daughter feeds, the son
does not feed. Not at all clear what that means. The גמרא
Gemara will unpack that. רבי שמעון יוחאי אומר, Rabbi Shimon Yochai Omer,
רבי שמעון יוחאי Rabbi Shimon Yochai says, זכרים יאכלו כולם נקבות לא
יאכלו. Zkharim Yokhlu Kulam N'kevot Lo Yokhlu. So if there are only
male children and she is pregnant, then the slaves can eat. The
male children can eat and the slaves can eat and her slaves
can eat. Now why is that? What if the fetus is a
boy and has a portion in the estate in the slaves? Why
is this not a problem? So basically the way the גמרא Gemara
will explain it, but I'll just tell you now, is because look,
there's only there's less than a 50% chance that a live baby
boy will be born from this pregnant woman. 50% chance it'll be
a boy, 50% chance it'll be a girl. If it's a girl,
then that does not create a problem in the, thank you, in
the ownership of the slaves, because the slaves are owned by the
live boys. The girl doesn't have a portion in the estate. And
if on the 50% chance that it's a boy, not every birth
ends in not every pregnancy ends in a live birth. So therefore
there's a less than a 50% chance, let's say it's a 48%
chance that a baby boy will be born. So therefore that's a
minority. You don't have to concern yourself with a minority. In the
majority of cases, מיעוטא לא חיישינן?
Miyuta lo chayshinan?
Yeah, exactly.
That's the position. So if there are already male children, we don't
have to worry about the fetus because it might be a girl
and won't affect the ownership and it might be a boy and
even if it's a boy it won't necessarily be born alive. Then
יאכלו. Yokhlu. נקבות, N'kevot, if they're girls, לא יאכלו. Lo Yokhlu. שמא
ימצא עובר זכר Shema Yimatze Ubar Zakhar
because maybe the boy will be a, the fetus will be a
male and then he'll have ownership over the slaves. ואין לבנות במקום
הבן כלום. V'ein La-Banot Bimqom Ha-Ben Klum. And the girls won't have
any portion of it. So the גמרא Gemara says, מאי איריא שמא
ימצא עובר זכר? Mai Irya Shema Yimatze Ubar Zakhar? I don't understand,
if there's all girls and she's pregnant, it doesn't matter whether the
fetus is a boy or a girl. תיפוק ליה דנקבה נמי פסלה.
Teipeiq Lei D'nekeva Nami Pasla. If she's a girl, then she splits
in the ownership of the slaves. And if she's a boy,
he gets all of the ownership of the slaves. Either way, if
right now there are girls in the family and this woman is
pregnant, this fetus will get a portion of the estate, either all
of it or a piece of it. So the גמרא Gemara says,
חדא. Chada. דנקבה נמי פסלה. dinkiva nami pasla. So the גמרא Gemara
says, okay, חדא ועוד קאמר. chada veod kaamar. You're right, this and
that. חדא chada number one, דנקבה נמי פסלה, dinkiva nami pasla, even
if she's a girl, then because there's only girls right now, she'll
get a portion of the estate. ועוד שמא ימצא עובר זכר, veod
shema yimatze ubar zachar, maybe there'll be a boy and then he'll
get the whole estate, ואם הבת במקום הבן כלום. veim habat bimkom
haban klum. Okay, so that's the idea about, you know, whether right
now there are boys or girls, the position of רבי ישמעאל בר
רבי יוסי. Rabbi Yishmael bar Rabbi Yossi. But now the גמרא Gemara
wants to understand why when there are boys, we don't have to
be concerned that the fetus is a boy and will have a
portion. So the גמרא Gemara says, זכרים יאכלו, zcharim yochlu, if it's
only boys they can eat, or the slaves can eat,
ואיכא עובר, veika ubar, what about the fetus?
Maybe that'll be a boy and he'll have a portion. No, קסבר
אין חוששין למיעוטא. kasavar ein choshshin lemiuta.
He's of the opinion you're not concerned yourself with the minority, even
though the minority is like a 48% minority. It's pretty amazing. But
nevertheless, you know, the possibility that it'll be born as a live
born is less than 50%.
So the גמרא Gemara says, ואי בעית אימא לעולם קסבר חוששין למיעוטא,
vei bayit eima leolam kasavar choshshin lemiuta, or maybe you are concerned
for this, especially when it's a 48% minority. But, דעבדינן ליה תקנתא,
deavdinan lei takanta,
but maybe he holds that there's a way of solving the problem
of the fetus and the fetus's ownership of partial ownership of the
estate. What's the way of solving it? דעבדינן ליה תקנתא, deavdinan lei
takanta, where were we? דעבדינן ליה תקנתא כרב נחמן אמר שמואל, deavdinan
lei takanta kerav nachman amar shmuel, like רב נחמן Rav Nachman in
the name of שמואל. Shmuel. דאמר רב נחמן אמר שמואל, deamar rav
nachman amar shmuel, in a general case about underage children when it
comes to divide the estate, יתומים שבאו לחלוק בנכסי אביהם, yetomim shebau
lachalok benichsei avihem,
orphans who are coming to divide the estate of their father, and
some of them are adults and some of them are not. So
בית דין מעמידין להם אפוטרופוס ובורר להם חלק יפה. beit din maamidin
lahem apotropos uborer lahem chelek yafe. בית
דין
Beit
Din assigns for them an אפוטרופוס, apotropos, some type of a, you
know, what's a good English word for this?
Caretaker. What? Executor. The executor is the one that takes the interests
of the dead. This is somebody that represents the interests of the
heir. Guardian. Steward. Okay. ובורר להם חלק יפה, uborer lahem chelek yafe,
and he, in their on their behalf, chooses for them a good
portion of the estate, sort of negotiates with the other brothers in
terms of how to divide it. הגדילו יכולים למחות. higdilu yocholim limchot.
Now what happens if now they become adults? So יכולים למחות. yocholim
limchot. According to this opinion, they actually can then say, actually, you
know, we don't think he made the right choice for us, and
they can reverse his choice. So they really get the best of
both worlds, right?
What does that mean?
I know, I know. Well, that's the next statement. But they get
the best of both worlds. Somebody gets to choose for them and
they can keep it if it worked out in their interest, and
if not, they can always reverse it. But רב נחמן דידיה אמר,
Rav Nachman didei amar, that's רב נחמן Rav Nachman in the name
of שמואל. Shmuel. רב נחמן Rav Nachman himself said,
הגדילו אין יכולים למחות. higdilu ein yocholim limchot. No, no, no. Even
once they become adults, they can't reverse the decision. דאם כן מה
כח בית דין יפה, deim ken ma koach beit din yafe, because
or else like what's the point of, you know, where's the power
of בית דין? Beit Din? The power of בית דין Beit Din
is to, you know, assign them and make it and make it
binding and make it, yeah, that they fully represent them. Anyway, we're
not going to get into that debate, but the point is that
he says that we can actually designate a portion. So he says,
oh, here's a perfect solution to the problem of the עובר. ubar.
We got this עובר, ubar, we got these slaves that can't eat
תרומה terumah now. Let בית דין Beit Din go ahead and create
a representative, an אפוטרופוס apotropos for the עובר, ubar, pick out which
portion of the estate is his, which slaves are his. Those slaves
won't eat, and all the other slaves will eat. And that's why
when... and that's why normally, you know, you can eat even if
she's pregnant, because even if she's pregnant, you know, then maybe you
know this אפוטרופוס apotropos solves the problem. So it's not because we're
not concerned it'll be a boy. Even if we are concerned it'll
be a boy, the אפוטרופוס apotropos solves the problem. Okay.
What happens to the idea that before the עובר ubar is born,
the living עבדים avadim don't have 100% access to the...
No, so that's what it's saying. So if this עובר ubar is
given out of the ten slaves, he's given these two, these two
don't eat. They're owned by the עובר ubar and the עובר ubar
can't cause them to eat. The other eight that are now owned
by the other brothers do eat.
It's the force of the אפוטרופוס apotropos therefore takes the עובר ubar
and those slaves sort of out of the...
Exactly. So as opposed to the עובר ubar owning a 20% of
every slave, he just owns two out of the ten slaves. And
the other eight slaves are fully owned by the other brothers and
therefore they can eat. Before the אפוטרופוס apotropos he owned 20% of
every slave. Right. Okay, so therefore business structure.
So then if the fetus is a woman...
so how does it work? So if the girls if what's left
are girls, then the אפוטרופוס apotropos won't help because then all of
the slaves might be owned by the male by the male fetus.
And what if the fetus is a girl?
Then certainly all the slaves can eat. Yeah, then they would have
to redistribute. Right. So that's true. This would all be done on
the assumption that it would be a boy. But at least it
would free up the other slaves. Okay, so that's obviously asserting something
in this ברייתא Baraita that isn't there, but it's saying that's how
we could solve it in the case of the fetus and it's
not because we're not concerned that it'll be born as a... live-born.
So the גמרא Gemara says, לימא דרב נחמן תנאי היא, Leima d'Rav
Nachman tanna'i hi,
so maybe, so why are the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma debated? Maybe
the position of רב נחמן Rav Nachman is debated, maybe whether you're
allowed to assign this
אפיטרופוס? apotropos? Says לא, lo, no. Forget the answer we just gave.
Everybody could hold of רב נחמן. Rav Nachman. Forget that whole answer,
we're not talking about that special case. They didn't assign an אפיטרופוס.
apotropos. והכא בחששינן למיעוטא
קמיפלגי. v'hacha b'chashinan l'miuta kamiflagi. It's funny, just completely reverses itself. That
was an interesting idea, but back to the simple sense. No, forget
the whole idea of assigning an אפיטרופוס. apotropos. The question is, if
it's a 48% chance that a baby boy will be born, right,
because 50% chance a boy and it might not be born alive,
it might not go to term. So is that a concern or
not? Okay, so that's, so that's the position, the last opinion, רבי
שמעון בר יוחאי Rabbi Shimon Bar Yochai said, if there's only boys
around, I'm not concerned about the fetus because it might not be
born as a live-born. Forget רב נחמן. Rav Nachman. Now we get
to the more cryptic statement of רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Ishmael the son
of רבי יוסי. Rabbi Yossi. Yes?
Is there a difference between this and like איסורים issurim or getting
back to the מיעוט המצוי, miut hamatzui, because in כשרות kashrut don't
we actually do חושש? choshesh?
Yeah, so it's a bit of איסור. issur. Yeah, I mean it's
very hard. I mean, תוספות Tosafot sort of has part of that
question as well about why you're not חושש choshesh more for מיעוט
miut here. It's a very strange statement. But it could also be
the whole question of the status of the unborn fetus and something
that's not לפנינו lefanenu and it's... but it's very bizarre that you
wouldn't be concerned for 48%. Anyway, let's keep on going. The גמרא
Gemara says like this: Okay, רבי ישמעאל בר רבי יוסי אומר משום
אביו. Rabbi Ishmael bar Rabbi Yossi omer mishum aviv. So now רבי
ישמעאל Rabbi Ishmael the son of רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi in the
name of his father: הבת מאכילה הבן אינו מאכיל. Habat ma'achilo, haben
eino ma'achilo.
If they're daughters, she allows the slave to eat, but sons don't
allow the slaves to eat. So what does that mean? מאי שנא
בן דלא מאכיל? Mai shna ben delo ma'achilo?
Why can the son not have the slaves eat? משום חלקו של
עובר, Mishum chelko shel ubar, because the עובר ubar has a portion.
What case over here?
We don't know yet. He basically sounds like if there's a boy
around
then the slaves can eat
and if there's a girl around the slaves can eat and if
there's a boy around they can't eat, which is like the exact
reverse of what we just said in the name of רבי שמעון
בן יוחאי. Rabbi Shimon ben Yochai. So that's what the גמרא Gemara
says. מאי שנא בן דלא מאכיל? Mai shna ben delo ma'achilo? If
there's a son the slaves can't eat. משום חלקו של עובר, Mishum
chelko shel ubar, because the עובר ubar has a portion. בת נמי
לא תאכיל משום חלקו של עובר? Bat nami letachil mi'chelko shel ubar?
And anyway all the more so if it's a girl the slaves
can't eat because the עובר ubar has a portion, either as a
girl or as a boy, even as a girl it's a portion.
So what's the story? אמר אביי, Amar Abaye, הכא בנכסים מועטים עסקינן.
hacha b'nechasim muatim askinan.
We're talking about again a special case. What's the special case? There's
a very small estate. Now the הלכה halacha by a small estate
is the sons have a right to inherit or they do inherit,
but the daughters have a right to be fed by the estate
until they basically get married. Okay, they're supported by the estate. No,
that's by any estate. But by a נכסים מועטים, small estate, the
point is that the daughters' the cost of supporting the girls until
they get married is equal to or greater than the actual assets
of the estate. So the הלכה halacha is that the girls' rights
trump the boys' inheritance and they're going to basically be completely supported
by the estate and even if it means not only that the
boys don't inherit but that the boys in order to just they
have to go begging in order to put food on the table,
because the girls are entitled to be supported, the boys aren't entitled
to anything, they inherit if there's what to inherit. Okay, so because
of that, this is a special case where the girls actually have
more ownership of the estate than the boys. Okay, so now let's
see how that's going to play out in terms of the slaves.
Okay, so let's take a look. הכא בנכסים מועטים עסקינן. Hacha b'nechasim
muatim askinan. We're talking about a
נכסים מועטים. small estate. כגון דאיכא בן בהדי בת. Kegon de'ika ben
bahadei bat. And there is a son and there is also a
girl. So let's take a look. So the case is הבת מאכילה,
habat ma'achilo, if there's a daughter around. So you've got the pregnant
woman. I'll draw it out here.
Okay, here's a boy,
okay, and here's the pregnant woman. Okay. Okay. And do you also
have a girl? So if it's הבן אינו מאכיל, haben eino ma'achilo,
right, let's start with הבן אינו מאכיל, haben eino ma'achilo, if it's
just a boy then the slaves can't eat. Why? Because obviously this
might be she might be pregnant with a boy and then he'll
have an equal portion and all of the problems. But, so that's
הבן אינו מאכיל. haben eino ma'achilo. If there's just a son alone
then the slaves can't eat because the עובר ubar might also have
a portion and there's no girls. But if there's also a בת,
bat, right, if there's also a בת, bat, then then the slaves
can eat. Why? Because what's going to happen now that there's a
daughter? She's going to get the entire estate, okay, because it's נכסים
מועטים, nechasim muatim, she's entitled to totally be supported by it. Okay,
so the slaves are owned by her. Now why doesn't this this
fetus ruin it? Well let's consider the two possibilities. Maybe he's a
boy. If he's a boy does he affect her ownership? No. No,
not in a מועט muat case. If he's a girl, does he
affect her ownership? Well, maybe shouldn't this girl also be entitled to
a portion? So the הלכה halacha is yeah, but since the reason
the girls eat is because of a Rabbinic, a Rabbinic ruling תקנה
takana or whatever, the Rabbis did not give those rights to the
fetus. They only gave those rights to the born girl. Okay, so
this is a case where if he's a boy and he has
a portion in the estate, he doesn't in this special case. If
it's a girl and she has a and girls have a right
to be supported by the estate, that's only once they're born. And
that's why if there's a בת, bat, if there's only a בן,
ben, the slaves can't eat. If there's a בת, bat, it all
goes to her at at that moment by נכסים מועטים. nechasim muatim.
When she gets born she does, not while she's a fetus.
It doesn't ruin it for everyone else.
Correct. Okay, so it says like this. So it says וכגון דאיכא
בן בהדי בת, uchegon de’ika ben behadi bat, ממה נפשך, mima nafshach,
either way. אי האי דמיעברא בן הוא, ei hai dem’abra ben hu,
if the one she's pregnant with is a boy, לאו עדיף מהאי
דקאי, lav adif mehai dekai, he's not better than the boy that's
already around, then in this case he isn't getting any portion of
it. אי בת היא, ei bat hi, and if it's a daughter,
אמאי אכלה, amai achla, why do girls eat in this case? בתקנתא
דרבנן, betakanta derabbanan, because of a Rabbinic edict. כמה דלא נפקא לאויר
העולם, kama dela nafka la’avir ha’olam, until she's actually born, לא תקינו
רבנן, lo takinu rabbanan, the Rabbis did not give her support while
she's while she's a fetus. They gave her support once she's born.
Okay, so that's a nice, you know, חידוש, chiddush, I mean, it's
reading a lot into the משנה, mishna, but it's a it's a
nice way to that it reverses this. Okay. במה אוקימתא? bema ukimta?
What are you saying the case is talking about? בנכסים מועטים, benechasim
muatim, a limited amount a small estate. אימא סיפא, eima seifa, but
look at the end of the ברייתא. braita. שמא ימצאו בזכר, shema
yimatze’u bazachar, this is in the statement of רבי שמעון בר יוחאי,
Rabbi Shimon bar Yochai, maybe the fetus will be a male ואין
הבנות במקום הבן כלום. ve’ein habanot bimkom haben klum. And then the
the boy will the boy will get it all. That was in
the statement of רבי שמעון בר יוחאי. Rabbi Shimon bar Yochai. So
that shows that so that shows you we're not talking about a
small estate. That's saying the boys would get it all. אדרבה בנכסים
מועטים דבנות נינהו, adaraba benechasim muatim de’banot ninhu,
if it were a small estate it would all be the girls'.
So okay, fine. סיפא אתא לנכסים מרובים. seifa ata lenechasim merubim.
Fine, the end of רבי שמעון בר יוחאי, Rabbi Shimon bar Yochai,
that's going by a big estate, but this statement of of רבי
ישמעאל בנו של רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yishmael beno shel Rabbi Yosi, that
was talking about this special case. אמר גמרא amar gemara says the
Gemara, ונכסים מועטים דבנות נינהו? venechasim muatim de’banot ninhu? If it's a
small estate, is it really the girls'? והאמר רבי אסי אמר רבי
יוחנן, ve’ha’amar Rabbi Assi amar Rabbi Yochanan, יתומים שקדמו ומכרו בנכסים מועטים,
yetomim shekadmu umachru benechasim muatim, מה שמכרו מכרו? ma shemachru machru?
So if the orphans went ahead and sold in a small estate,
the boys, then it's a binding sale. Right? Because it's funny, this
idea that even though the girls are entitled to be supported by
it, if you ask the question, who actually has title to the
property? Right? So yes, the girls have a right to be supported
by it and that right might completely, you know, exhaust the the
what or the you know whatever estate, you know, right, like totally,
you know, empty out the entire inheritance. But until and and the
boys might have to go begging for food because their right entitles
them to be supported. But right now, who has title to it?
The title presumably is still the boys', right? The the boys own
it and the girls have a right to be supported by it.
It's like a debt. Right? And so but ultimately the title is
the boys'. And that's why if the boys go ahead and sell
it, it's a binding sale. They have so how can you say
that the slaves eat by virtue of the girl and they're the
girl's slaves? They're not. They're the boy's slaves that the girls have
rights to be fed by, but ultimately they're the boy's slaves. So
this doesn't solve the problem.
What about if it's the boy sells, aren't they still obligated with
the proceeds from the sale to feed the women?
That might be, but it still proves that they have that yeah
but but still proves that the title is the boys', the title
isn't
the girls'. Okay.
So אלא מאי? ela mai? בת דקתני, bat de’katani, fine. All right.
If we concede that point, we have to say what does it
mean that it says girls feed? It doesn't mean girls. It means
אם. em. It means mother. Which is quite a bizarre read. Okay.
Which is that the mother the woman feeds her slaves. That even
in this case of עובר ubar or whatever, right, if the woman
can eat, her slaves can eat. But אי הכי, ei hachi, and
then it says the בן ben doesn't feed. It means the father.
Okay. It means that the נכסי דאמיה nichsei d’imei eat, the
the stuff that's of the mother's estate eat, but the stuff that's
of the father's estate don't eat. היינו רבי יוסי, hainu Rabbi Yosi,
so it's just what Rabbi Yosi said, right, that if there's born
children and a pregnant child, then her slaves eat and his slaves
don't eat. So כולה רבי ישמעאל בנו של רבי יוסי קתני. kula
Rabbi Yishmael beno shel Rabbi Yosi katani. Fine, it's it was all
an expansion of a teaching that רבי ישמעאל בנו של רבי יוסי
Rabbi Yishmael beno shel Rabbi Yosi said and so it's really not
different than what his father what we had quoted in the name
of his father originally, which is obviously either way those are two
very hard reads of the ברייתא braita that son and daughter mean
father and mother. All right, that is the end of the whole
slaves and the pregnant and the status of the fetus. Moving on.
Yes.
Part of this part of this argument was about males being in
the minority.
Yeah.
of pregnancies though end in live birth? I'm sure that that ultimately
will still lead to less than 50% of live boys being born.
Actually it's still a little over 50% in most of the... Really?
Even including miscarriages? Oh yeah.
Really? It depends on when you start counting. Yeah.
In the developed... anyway in the developed world there
aren't that many miscarriages.
All right, well the world of the time of the גמרא Gemara
wasn't yet the developed world. Yes, Dov?
Maybe we didn't specify but the
assumptions are עובר ubar has a right.
Right. It's not so obvious. Right, well that's why the גמרא Gemara
says that that is possibly what's debated, right? You know, whether מזכה
לעובר קנה או לא קנה. mazakeh l'ubar kanah or lo kanah. So
it is true that the entire סוגיא sugya basically bought into רבי
יוסי Rabbi Yosi both assumptions. Number one that the עובר ubar inherits
and number two that the slave doesn't eat while he's not yet
unborn. Now the second one seems like מפקפק, m'pakek, I don't know,
you know, that's like that's but but the idea that the עובר
ubar inherits is, you know, but that's why the גמרא Gemara did
quote an opposite position about that, right? About, you know, שמואל Shmuel
says it is true but there's another position that it isn't true
and you could fundamentally debate that of course. Right, the גמרא Gemara
never expanded on that issue. That's discussed elsewhere whether מזכה לעובר קנה
mazakeh l'ubar kanah and what are the, you know, here the focus
is much more on the תרומה terumah aspect, right? But yeah, the
תרומה terumah aspect builds on the assumption that the עובר ubar gets
a portion in the estate and that gets developed in a different
גמרא. Gemara.
Yeah, so in certain purposes of business of
inheritance law the עובר ubar can be conceptualized as an independent being.
Yes, according to the assumptions of this גמרא. Gemara. Yes.
פיקוח נפש pikuach nefesh it's part of the mother.
Well yeah, yeah, I mean so that, right, that does become right
interesting questions of, you know, עובר ירך אמו ubar yerech imo and
an עובר ubar an entity to have to have ownership and then
what are the implications then of that in terms of questions of
like abortion, you know, can you have interesting mixes of status there.
Right, so that's that is a very interesting question. Yes. Okay, so
now moving on. Still talking about starts with the עובר ubar but
it gets more broadly here and this is still within issues about
eating תרומה. terumah. So let's take a look. העובר ha'ubar so we've
already talked about the fetus, that the fetus is not yet his
mother can't eat on behalf of him and the fetus again is
the worst both ways. Forget the slaves for a minute. If you
have a בת כהן bat kohen married to ישראל Yisrael and then
her husband dies she goes back to eat... the question if a
woman has children, you know, has it's the same question but it's
with reverse implications based on who the woman is and who she's
married to. If she doesn't have children she goes back she if
she has children she's still connected to her dead husband's house. If
she doesn't have children she goes back to her father's house her
virtual father's house. How does that play out? If she's a בת
כהן bat kohen married to ישראל Yisrael and she has children then
she's still connected to her dead husband's ישראל's Yisrael house she doesn't
go back to eating תרומה. terumah. No children she goes back to
her father כהן's kohen house she goes back to eating תרומה. terumah.
The reverse is true if it's a בת ישראל bat Yisrael married
to a כהן. kohen. Has children still connected to her dead husband's
house כהן kohen eats תרומה. terumah. No children goes back to her
father ישראל's Yisrael house doesn't eat תרומה. terumah. If there's a fetus
so she is caught between the two worlds. She's not she's connected
enough to her husband that if she is a בת כהן bat
kohen married to ישראל Yisrael she can't eat תרומה terumah because she's
still connected enough to her dead husband she has a she's, you
know, she's carrying a fetus. Okay? But she's not yet totally fully
connected so if she's a בת ישראל bat Yisrael married to a
כהן kohen she's not yet entitled to eat תרומה. terumah. Okay so
the fetus is in this gray zone. Enough connected that it takes
her out of her father's house and would disqualify her from eating
תרומה terumah if she was a בת כהן. bat kohen. But not
connected enough so it doesn't make her fully part of her dead
husband's house to entitle her to eat if she is a בת
ישראל bat Yisrael married to a כהן. kohen. Is that clear? This
is how it does so sort of things. Okay and now we're
going to look at a list of ways a list of scenarios
where this woman is quasi-connected to her husband. Enough connected so not
part of her father's house and can't eat if her father's a
כהן kohen but not connected enough so she can't eat if she's
a ישראל Yisrael and her husband is a כהן. kohen. So the
עובר ubar is one example we're going to see a series of
examples. What about this woman is right בוגרת bogeret or no?
Right. And if
but if she goes regularly let's say she's just married whatever.
It's not about going to her father's house conceptually.
If let's say she visits her...
has nothing to do with the literal father's house.
Okay העובר והיבם ha'ubar v'hayavam so if she has a fetus or
let's say she's got remember the יבם yavam she's got a brother-in-law.
Okay so think about that's a case of זיקה zikah right? So
that's a case of and the let's say the brother-in-law's a כהן
kohen and she's a בת ישראל bat Yisrael or the reverse she's
a בת כהן bat kohen and the the brother-in-law's a ישראל. Yisrael.
That's a perfect case of this gray area part connected partly but
not fully. Enough out of her father's house but not enough into...
to her husband's house. Or here's another example, אירוסין. erusin. Even if
there's real קידושין kiddushin but not yet נישואין, nisuim, so she's not
yet no longer part of her father's house, can't eat by virtue
of her father, but she's not yet fully part of her husband's
house, can't eat by virtue of her husband. Okay, והחרש v'hacheresh or
if it's a marriage to a deaf-mute, which halachically is not considered
to be a בר דעת, bar daas, somebody who is a sort
of a legal, you know, have of legally of of of of
of sound not sound mind but of a whatever of of of
of competence, thank you. And therefore it's like a rabbinic קידושין, kiddushin,
so it also would sort of be in this mid-gray zone. ובן
תשע שנים ויום אחד, uven tesha shanim veyom echad, and nine years
and a day. Now it's not exactly clear what the relevance of
nine years and a day is. It might refer to an act
of יבום yibum done with somebody who's nine years and a day
in terms of ביאה, biah, but we'll see that in the גמרא.
Gemara. But that somehow is also considered this gray zone. In all
these cases פוסלים, poslim, they invalidate her. If she was a בת
כהן bas kohen and this was a relationship to a ישראל, Yisrael,
it's enough of a relationship that it invalidates her, takes her out
of her father's house. ולא מאכילים, v'lo maachilim, but it's not strong
enough so if the man is a כהן kohen and she's a
בת ישראל, bas Yisrael, it's not a strong enough relationship to allow
her to eat. It's this gray zone. Now, ספק בן תשע שנים
ויום אחד ספק אינו, safek ben tesha shanim veyom echad safek eino,
if it's the same would be true even if it's doubtful whether
he's nine years and a day. We haven't really explained what the
nine-year case is. ספק הביא שתי שערות ספק לא הביא, safek hevi
shtei searos safek lo hevi, or in the case of let's say
case of קידושין, kiddushin, אירוסין. erusin. Let's say he is a questionable
adult. We don't know if he has two pubic hairs or, you
know, if he's 13 years old presumably we know if he's 13
years old. So we don't know if he's a halachic adult and
he does קידושין kiddushin with this woman. So why don't we say,
oh, it's only a ספק קידושין, safek kiddushin, she should still continue
eating if she's a בת כהן? bas kohen? No. Even though it's
only a ספק safek and it's a ספק safek of this status,
that's enough to invalidate her from eating. Now here's another scenario not
related to the above, but it's also a question of a ספק.
safek. נפל הבית עליו ועל בת אחיו. nafal habayis alav v'al bas
achiv. Okay,
now we're getting back to a classic יבום yibum case. Okay, he
is married to his niece, alright, and and no kids. It's going
to be a יבום yibum case. And a house collapsed on him
and his wife, who happens to be his niece. Now he happens
to also have another co-wife, a צרה. tzara. Remember all these fun
cases? So, is his brother, father of his wife, is his brother
has a מצוה mitzvah of יבום yibum to the surviving co-wife? So
it depends on the order of death. If first his his wife
died and then he died, so then when he died he left
behind just one wife, the surviving co-wife, and his brother has a
מצוה mitzvah of יבום. yibum. But if the order of death was
the reverse, first he died, then he left behind two wives, one
of which was his brother's daughter, and therefore the co-wife is out
of the picture, right? There's no מצוה mitzvah of יבום. yibum. So
what's the story? נפל הבית עליו ועל בת אחיו ואין ידוע איזה
מהן מת ראשון צרתה חולצת ולא מתייבמת. nafal habayis alav v'al bas
achiv ve'ein yadu'a eizeh mehen meis rishon tzarasah choletzes v'lo misyabemes. So
the co-wife does חליצה chalitza not יבום yibum because we don't know
if you can do יבום. yibum. Okay, that was complete sorry that
was a complete throwback. What? Well, no, the רש"י Rashi says it's
in the משנה Mishnah because we're talking about we mentioned יבם yavam
and we're talking about ספק safek cases, it was really a total
digression. Okay. Now, גמרא. Gemara. העובר. ha'ubar. אי בת כהן
לישראל היא, ei bas kohen l'Yisrael hi, if it's a כהן kohen
woman married to a ישראל, Yisrael, he פסלה, paslah,
then the עובר ubar invalidates, כי נעוריה, ki'neuraha, that she only goes
back to her father's house when it's like her youth. פרט למעוברת,
perat l'muberes, to exclude a case of pregnancy is not enough reverting
to her original state. If she's still pregnant she's still somewhat connected.
And therefore she can't go back to eat תרומה teruma like she
used to. אי בת ישראל לכהן היא, ei bas Yisrael l'kohen hi,
and if she's a בת ישראל bas Yisrael married to a כהן,
kohen, בת לכהן היא, bas l'kohen hi, לא מאכיל, lo maachil, then
the relationship is not strong enough to let her eat. Because ילוד
מאכיל שאין ילוד מאכיל, yalud maachil she'ein yalud maachil, only a as
we were talking about before, a born child can entitle the slaves
or the mother to eat, an unborn child is not yet enough.
It doesn't quote a פסוק, pasuk, but that's what we're asserting. Okay,
so that's the gray zone. היבם, hayavam, a brother-in-law. אי בת
כהן לישראל היא, ei bas kohen l'Yisrael hi,
if it's a בת כהן bas kohen and this brother-in-law is a
ישראל, Yisrael, פסלה, paslah, he invalidates her, ושבה אל בית אביה, veshava
el beis aviha, she can return- because when does she go back
to eating תרומה? teruma? When she returns to her father's house. פרט
לשומרת יבם, perat l'shomeres yavam, she can't return yet, she's still bound
up, she needs חליצה chalitza to free her. אי בת ישראל לכהן
היא, ei bas Yisrael l'kohen hi, and if he's a כהן kohen
and she's a בת ישראל, bas Yisrael, לא מאכיל לה, lo maachil
lah, he doesn't feed her because קנין כספא אמר רחמנא, kinyan kaspa
amar Rachmana, it has to be like his acquisition of money. There
we go back to a woman being a קנין. kinyan. וקנין דאחיו
הוא, vekinyan d'achiv hu, and this
is a woman his brother married. Now of course once he does
יבום, yibum, then they'll be fully like his wife, but at this
stage it's not enough of a relationship. Okay, והאירוסין, veha'erusin, it's almost
a קל וחומר kal vachomer from the case of אירוסין erusin where
you actually did קידושין kiddushin and not נישואין nisuim that's not enough.
So let's see why. אי בת כהן לי- ei bas kohen li-
now they're- the guy isn't dead in the case of אירוסין. erusin.
In the case of אירוסין. erusin. Okay, here we're now to a
case where the guy is alive. Okay, but the relationship to this
man is still grey because it's אירוסין erusin not נישואין. nissu'in. אי
בת כהן לישראל היא ei bat Kohen l'Yisrael hi פסלה, pasla, then
he invalidates her דהקניא בהויה, d'hakanya bahavaya, because it says, right, that
it's because the פסוק pasuk says ובת כהן כי תהיה לאיש זר,
Ubat Kohen ki tihye l'ish zar, if she belongs to, you know,
again, that קנין kinyan idea or is to another man. So once
there's some קנין, kinyan, she's no longer in her father's house. Again,
although interestingly because the whole idea of נישואין nissu'in conceptually is leaving
the father's house and going, right, to the groom's house, to the
husband's house. Conceptually she's in the father's house after אירוסין erusin until
נישואין. nissu'in. So you could say oh she's in the father's house,
but no, that connection to that other man, that's enough to make
it not fully seen as her father's house and it's, or even
if she's in her father's house, she's also to another man if
you want to put it that way. And
therefore she no longer eats based on her father's house. ואי בת
ישראל לכהן היא, V'ei bat Yisrael l'kohen hi, and if it's a
בת ישראל Bat Yisrael married to a כהן, Kohen, so לא מאכלה
lo machla משום דעולא. mishum d'Ulla. Now here's an interesting question: why
is קידושין kiddushin not enough to let a woman eat תרומה Terumah
if it's קידושין kiddushin to a כהן? Kohen? So this is a
מחלוקת בבלי ירושלמי. machlokes Bavli Yerushalmi. Right, the בבלי Bavli says that
the reason a woman married to a כהן Kohen eats תרומה, Terumah,
it says
קנין כספו הוא יאכל בלחמו. Kinyan kaspo hu yochal blachmo. His acquisition
of money can eat. So the גמרא Gemara says acquisition of money
is slave and wife, because you do קידושין kiddushin with money. Again,
that קנין kinyan idea. So in principle, after קידושין kiddushin before נישואין,
nissu'in, a woman married to a כהן Kohen actually could eat. But
there's עולא'ס Ulla's statement. עולא Ulla says in practice though, where's this
woman living during the period of קידושין kiddushin before נישואין? nissu'in? In
her father's house. What's going to happen if the כהן Kohen sends
her תרומה? Terumah? She's going to wind up sharing it with her
father and her brother and so on. So it's a rabbinic concern.
So according to actually the בבלי, Bavli, הלכתית halachically she actually can
eat at this stage. ירושלמי Yerushalmi actually says no. She doesn't eat
by virtue of קנין כספו, kinyan kaspo, she eats by issue of
ביתו הם יאכלו בלחמו. beiso hem yochlu blachmo. And the idea of
בית, bayis, household, is only after נישואין. nissu'in. So actually the בבלי,
Bavli, the ירושלמי Yerushalmi says that it's actually biblical that she does
not eat until נישואין, nissu'in, which is consistent with these ideas that
this is a grey zone, you know, and it's not rabbinic, it
really lives in both worlds. Okay, so that's that.
Just so what was עולא? Ulla? He said all that?
עולא Ulla didn't say the ירושלמי. Yerushalmi. עולא Ulla said because we're
afraid she'll feed her father and brother. Okay, והחרש, v'hacheresh, if it's
a deaf-mute. So again, this is a whole important area of הלכה
halacha about how the status of חרש cheresh changed once they created
these schools for the deaf and so on, and realized you know,
they were intelligent. But at this stage anyway, they're treated as not
competent. So אי בת כהן לישראל היא, ei bat Kohen l'Yisrael hi,
if she's a בת כהן Bat Kohen married to a ישראל, Yisrael,
פסלה דקניא בתקנתא דרבנן. pasla d'hakanya betakanata d'rabbanan. Because the rabbis recognized
that even if a חרש cheresh was not seen as sort of
fully competent, he was certainly at a higher level than let's say
a שוטה, shoteh, who is somebody that really had no, you know,
was like insane or whatever, or
somebody who had like very, very low intelligence. And therefore a חרש
cheresh at least rabbinically had a rabbinic institution of marriage. So that
rabbinic institution was enough to remove her from her father's
house, even though biblically she really could still eat in that case.
ואי בת ישראל לכהן היא, V'ei bat Yisrael l'kohen hi, and obviously
though if she's a בת ישראל Bat Yisrael married to a כהן,
Kohen, the rabbinic institution isn't going to be enough to entitle her
to eat. קנין כספו אמר רחמנא והאי לאו בר קניני הוא. Kinyan
kaspo amrah Rachmana v'hai lav bar kinyanei. It has to really be,
again, the acquisition, and this is something that biblically it is not
a קידושין, kiddushin, so clearly she cannot eat based on that. Now
we get to, let's just get a little further. Now we get
to the בן תשע שנים ויום אחד, ben tesha shanim v'yom echad,
which is the one that was less clear what the case was.
It's a קידושין kiddushin and an acquisition.
Yes. So how can because it's only rabbinic. What?
Which is rabbinic?
The חרש'ס cheresh's ability to do קידושין kiddushin is only rabbinic. Okay,
so biblically it's not
a marriage. Rabbinically, but not biblically. So rabbinically it's enough to invalidate
her from her father's house, but because it's not biblical it's not
enough to entitle her to eat if he's a כהן. Kohen. Okay.
ובן תשע שנים, V'ben tesha shanim, nine years old. קסלקא דעתך בששימש
יבם לבן תשע ויום אחד, kasalka daitech b'sheshimes yavam l'ben tesha v'yom
echad, right because תשע שנים tesha shanim is usually about sex, that
that's considered an act of sex. So the relevant case would be
that she was a woman waiting for יבום, yibbum, the brother-in-law was
nine years old and a day, could be an act of sex,
and he went and had sex with her. So okay, what's the
problem? It's יבום. yibbum. So let's take a look. So למאי? l'mai?
אי למפסל, ei l'mifsul, if it's to
invalidate, קטן נמי מיפסל פוסל. katan nami mifsul pasul. Meaning that the
fact that she is a בת כהן Bat Kohen and she can't
eat because of her connection to this boy, so even if he
was less than nine years old, if she here is, even if
the brother is a three-year-old or a one-year-old, she's still a
שומרת יבם. shomeres yavam. So if it's that this boy is preventing
her from being she's a בת כהן bat kohen from being part
of her father's house and eating, then forget whether he's had sex
with her, not had sex with her, whatever. If he's one day
old, he prevents her from going back to her father's house. She's
still bound up until there's either חליצה chalitzah or יבום. yibum. So
even even less than nine years
old. אכילה? achilah? So the point is no, that whether he's entitled
to have her eat on his behalf. So גדול נמי לא מאכיל.
gadol nami lo ma'achil. Before sex has been done, the גמרא Gemara
is assuming we haven't had sex yet. So even as an adult
she can't eat yet until they consummate.
אמר אביי הכא ביבם בן תשע שנים ויום אחד הבא על יבמתו
עסקינן. amar Abaye hacha biyavam ben tesha shanim veyom echad haba al
yevamto askinan. No, no, we're talking about that they had sex. Okay,
and here's the חידוש: chiddush: דמדאורייתא קני ליה. dimde'oraisa kani lei. Biblically,
it's a good act of יבום. yibum. So so now that he's
that they've had sex, she should—and this boy is a כהן—she kohen
should be entitled to
eat. סלקא דעתך אמינא הואיל ודאורייתא קני ליה בביאה וביאתו ביאה. salka
da'atcha amina ho'il ude'oraisa kani lei bevi'ah uvi'aso bi'ah. Since their sex
is sex, אימא תיכול, eima seichol, and so he's a כהן, kohen,
she should be allowed to eat. קא משמע לן עשו ביאת בן
תשע שנים ויום אחד כמאמר בגדול. ka mashma lan asu bi'as ben
tesha shanim veyom echad kemamar begadol. Yes, biblically you're right, but rabbinically,
even though this act of sex is a complete act of יבום,
yibum, rabbinically we look at it as only מאמר, ma'amar, as though
that the יבום yibum has not been completed. And it's a stronger
relationship, but it's not yet a full relationship. And therefore that's a
nice read of the משנה. mishnah. Nine years old and a day,
they've had sex, you might think she's entitled to eat. No, rabbinically
this is still in the gray zone and she's not entitled to
eat.
He's too young. Okay, אמר ליה רבא, amar lei Rava, that's a
nice read, let's see what רבא Rava says. אי הכי, i hachi,
סיפא דקתני ספק בן תשע שנים ויום אחד ספק שאינו. seifa dekasani
safek ben tesha shanim veyom echad safek she'eino. The משנה mishnah says
this is true even if he's not necessarily if it's doubtful if
he's nine years old. So רבא Rava says I don't get it.
השתא ודאי בן תשע לא מאכיל. hashta vadai ben tesha lo ma'achil.
Of course she can't eat if he's definitely nine years old and
it's definitely an act of sex biblically and she still can't eat.
ספק מיבעיא? safek mibaya? Of course if he might be younger it's
not going to work. Okay, so the end of the משנה mishnah
doesn't work
according to you.
The end of the משנה mishnah sounds like that if he were
definitely younger it would be better. According to this, if he's definitely
younger it would be even worse. אלא אמר רבא, ela amar Rava,
says רבא, Rava, בבן תשע שנים ויום אחד דהנך פסולין תני. beven
tesha shanim veyom echad dehanech pesulin tani. We're not talking about יבום
yibum anymore. We're talking about people that are actually invalidate the woman.
And this is going to be the next משנה. mishnah. Remember this
is another theme we keep on going back to: that if there
is basically
somebody, a ממזר, mamzer, an עבד, eved, any type of person whose
act of sex is forbidden, even a even a לאו, lav, not
a כרת, kares, and has sex with this woman, she now can
becomes like a חללה chalalah or זונה zonah depending on the case,
and now can no longer marry a כהן. kohen. And if she
was a בת כהן, bas kohen, also can't eat תרומה terumah once
she's had this forbidden act of sex. So רבא Rava says that's
the case. We're talking about she's had sex with somebody that would
that she's that is she's forbidden to and that would actually change
her status. So once he's nine years and a day, that invalidates
her. Okay, not—so it's not really a gray zone, it really completely
invalidates her. Okay, so let's take a look.
So it can be at וביאת גדול uvi'as gadol then.
It's not וביאת גדול, uvi'as gadol, בבן תשע שנים ויום אחד דהנך
פסולין תני, beven tesha shanim veyom echad dehanech pesulin tani, the פסולין
pesulin people, דפסלי בביאתן. depasli bevi'asan. They invalidate. Like we taught in
the ברייתא: beraisa: בן תשע שנים ויום אחד גר, ben tesha shanim
veyom echad ger, if it's the all these following pieces, גר עמוני
מואבי, ger Amoni Moavi, if he's a convert who was an Ammonite
or a Moabite, right, who you're not allowed to, לא יבא עמוני
בקהל ה' Lo yavo Amoni bikhal Hashem etc. Or so there's a
negative prohibition of having them marry even if they convert. מצרי אדומי
Mitzri Edomi or
an Egyptian or an Edomite for before the third generation. כותי נתין
חלל וממזר Kusi Nasin chalal umamzer or a Samaritan and a נתין,
Nasin, assuming that these people are not fully Jews, we won't get
into that right now. חלל, chalal, so a כהן kohen who is
a חלל chalal makes a woman a חללה chalalah with his act
of sex or ממזר. mamzer. So all of these people are forbidden
acts of sex or a חלל, chalal, it's not a forbidden act
of sex but it makes the woman a חללה. chalalah. Anyway, and
all these cases שבא על הכהנת ולביאת ישראלית sheba al hakohenes ule'vi'as
Yisraelis had sex with either a woman, whether she's a בת כהן
bas kohen or just a normal ישראלית, Yisraelis, פסלוה, pasluha, invalidate her.
So if it's a בת כהן, bas kohen, prevent her from eating
תרומה, terumah, and if it's a ישראלית, Yisraelis, prevent her from marrying
a כהן. kohen. Okay, so he says although the first cases in
the משנה mishnah were all these cases of being in this gray
zone, partly connected to the husband, partly not and therefore not eating,
now we're talking about a different issue. The reason she doesn't eat
is no gray zone, is that she's had sex and it's invalidated
her. But the point is even though the kid was only nine
years old. And now we understand even if it's only a ספק
safek if he was nine years old, she's still invalidated even on
the basis of the ספק. safek. Okay, והא, veha, so that's his
read of the משנה, mishnah, which the גמרא Gemara keeps to. והא
מדקתני סיפא, veha midekasani seifa, the end of the משנה, mishnah, not
the משנה mishnah we read now. but the משנה *Mishnah* we're going
to read that follows this, which is seen as the end of
our משנה *Mishnah*, the end of the משנה *Mishnah* said, אם אינם
ראויים לבוא בישראל הרי אלו
פוסלים *im einam reu'im lavo b'Yisrael harei elu poslim*,
if she had sex with people that are not able to be
part of the you know to marry with Jews, they invalidate her.
So that's going to be the following משנה's *Mishnah's* going to talk
about sex with somebody that she's not allowed to have sex with.
מכלל דרישא לאו lav, בפסולים עסקינן *michlal d'reisha lav b'psulim askinan*, so
you see that we're talking here not yet in the case of
people that are invalid people of having sex with. So the גמרא
gemara *Gemara* says, No, there are two categories. רישא פסולי קהל *reisha
psulei kahal*, here we're talking about people that are not allowed to
marry not only כהונה *kehunah* problems, not allowed to marry even with
a ישראל Yisrael, *Yisrael*, right? עמונים *Ammonim*, מואבים *Moavim*, מצרים *Mitzrim*, ממזר
*mamzer*, it's not about כהונה *kehunah*. That's one category of forbidden sexual
acts. וסיפא *v'seifa*, the next משנה *Mishnah*, where it's going to talk
about forbidden sexual acts, is the פסולי כהונה *psulei kehunah*, people that
are unique to כהנים Kohanim, *Kohanim*: גרושה לכהן *grushah l'kohen*, אלמנה לכהן
גדול *almanah l'kohen gadol*. Not necessarily, because on the one hand it's
because more כהונה *kehunah* specific it might have more implications for כהונה
*kehunah*. If it's more general, then it might be just seen as
more weighty. Okay, so the end is, and this is pointing us
to what the next משנה's *Mishnah's* going to be about, is not
this interesting gray zone, partly connected to her father's house, partly to
her husband. It's just about sex with forbidden acts of sex make
this woman אסורה לכהן *asurah l'kohen* and make her חללה *chalalah* or
make her זונה *zonah* or whatever, and one of those categories, and
also make her unable to eat תרומה terumah *terumah*. And now we're
going to turn our attention exactly to those issues. So let's take
a look. גופא *gufa*, בן תשע שנים ויום אחד *ben tesha shanim
v'yom echad*. Okay, nine years and a day. Whether he is a
גר *ger*, עמוני *Ammoni*, מואבי *Moavi*, whether he's a convert of an
Ammonite or Moabite. מצרי *Mitzri*, אדומי *Edomi*, כותי *Kuti*, נתין *netin*, חלל
*chalal*, ממזר *mamzer* שבא על כוהנת ולוויה וישראלית פסלה paslah, *sheba al
kohenet u'levi'yah v'yisraelit paslah*. Okay, that's what we quoted. Now we get
the end of this, right? רבי
יוסי אומר *Rabbi Yosei omer*, Rabbi
Yosei says... Now, by the way, I know Dov you like this,
that's the difference between גופא *gufa* and אמר מר *amar mar*. So
גופא *gufa* is we're going to go back to what we quoted
and we're quoting it in full. So here you see exactly that.
The first line we already quoted. But now we're quoting the end
of the ברייתא *beraita*. רבי יוסי אומר *Rabbi Yosei omer*, כל שזרעו
פסול פוסל *kol she'zaro pasul posel*, anybody whose children is invalid will
invalidate this woman through this act of sex. וכל ve-chol. שאין זרעו
פסול אינו פוסל *v'kol she'ein zaro pasul eino posel*, anybody whose child
is not
invalid will not invalidate the woman. So what type of a person
is forbidden to have sex with, but the child is not forbidden?
Can you think about that? What type of a person is invalid
to have sex with, but the child is not problematic? She was
already belongs to someone else.
What do you mean belongs?
Oh, you mean forbidden because she's a married woman or something like
that. Okay, but we're talking here about the man. That's true, by
a woman you would have that. So what about somebody who's only
forbidden up to three generations? And you're dealing with the third generation.
Oh, right. So he's right at the cusp of going in, right?
Anyway, we'll see about what רבי יוסי *Rabbi Yosei* means. But רבי
יוסי *Rabbi Yosei* says it's only when the child would be invalid
does he invalidate the woman. רבן שמעון בן גמליאל אומר *Rabban Shimon
ben Gamliel omer*, כל שאתה נושא בתו אתה נושא אלמנותו *kol she'ata
nosei bito ata nosei almanato*. Anybody who you could marry his daughter,
you could marry his widow, the woman he had sex with. וכל
ve-chol שאי אתה נושא בתו אי אתה נושא אלמנותו *v'kol she'ei ata
nosei bito ei ata nosei almanato*. If you couldn't marry his daughter,
you can't marry you, the כהן kohen *kohen* meaning, cannot marry his
widow. He doesn't invalidate the woman. Sounds very much like the previous
point, right? About what's the status of the child depends on, determines
the status of the woman. We'll see about that in the גמרא
gemara *Gemara*.
Okay, מנא הני מילי *mna hani mili*? Let's get started. Where do
you know this idea, this basic idea that sex with a man
that you're not allowed to have sex with, if a woman has
sex with such a man that's biblically forbidden, even if it's a
simple forbidden of a לאו *lav*, that it invalidates her to marry
a כהן kohen. *kohen*, and if she's a כוהנת *kohenet* it invalidates
her to eat תרומה terumah. *terumah*? מנא הני מילי *mna hani mili*?
אמר רב יהודה אמר רב *amar Rav Yehudah amar Rav*, אמר קרא
*amar kra*, the פסוק pasuk *pasuk* says, ובת כהן כי תהיה לאיש
זר u'Bat Kohen ki tihiyeh l'ish zar, *u'vat kohen ki tihyeh l'ish
zar*. Now the simple sense of the verse is she's married to
a foreign man, means a non-כהן kohen *kohen*. And once she's married
to a non-כהן kohen *kohen*, she can no longer eat the תרומה
terumah, *terumah* of her father's house. Okay, but we're going to read
it the following way: כיון שנבעלה לפסול לה *keivan she'niv'alah l'pasul lah*.
זר zar *zar* means somebody that's totally foreign, somebody you shouldn't be
having sex with, somebody who is forbidden to you. Once she has
had sex with somebody that is forbidden to her, פסלה paslah, *paslah*,
she is invalidated for eating תרומה terumah. *terumah*. So as opposed to
just during the period you're married to a non-כהן kohen *kohen* don't
eat תרומה terumah. *terumah*, and if he dies you go back and
eat תרומה terumah, *terumah*, that's the פשט pshat, *pshat*. We're saying if
you ever have sex with a full זר zar, *zar*, somebody who
you're forbidden to, you're completely invalidated from ever eating תרומה terumah. *terumah*
in the future. Okay? So that doesn't tell about being אסור *asur*
to marry a כהן kohen *kohen*, but it invalidates her תרומה terumah,
*terumah*. So the גמרא gemara *Gemara* says, האי מיבעי ליה *hai mibai
lei*? But one minute, we need this for the פשט *pshat*? דקאמר
רחמנא בת כהן Bat Kohen דמינסבא לזר לא תאכל *d'ka'amar Rachmana bat
kohen d'minsva l'zar lo tochal*, a בת כהן Bat Kohen, *bat kohen*
who's married to a non-כהן kohen *kohen* can't eat תרומה terumah *terumah*.
You need it for the פשט *pshat*. No, that we could have
figured out somewhere else. ההיא ושבה אל בית אביה כנעוריה מלחם אביה
תאכל. No, we could have figured it out from later, where it
says that if the guy dies then she can go back and
eat in her fa... the תרומה terumah, from her father's house. So
implicitly we can figure out that while she's married she can't. So
the גמרא Gemara says no, not דוקא, davka, we can learn it
מדקאמר רחמנא ושבה אל בית אביה תאכל מכלל דמעיקרא לא אכלה. mide-ka'amar
rachmana v'shava el beis aviha tochal miklal de-me'ikara lo achla. So we
could have figured it out from the end. So here it says
כי תהיה, ki tihye, שיהא בה הויה, she-yehai ba havaya, that's a
separate issue. הגמרא gemara says no, אי מההיא, ei me-hahi, I would
have just inferred it from after the husband dies she can go
back, הויא אמינא לאו הבא מכלל עשה עשה. hava amina lav haba
michlal asei asei. That okay, from there I can infer she's not
allowed while she's married, but that's only a negative idea 'don't eat
while you're married' that's inferred from a positive 'after he dies, go
back'. Okay? And it only has the weight of a מצוה עשה.
mitzvat asei. I need the תורה Torah to black and white say
it's a negative prohibition and it's forbidden. כתב רחמנא האי ללאו, ketav
rachmana hai le-lav, the תורה Torah had to say when she's married
to a non-כהן kohen don't eat, to make it a real negative
prohibition, not to tell you this new idea of sex with a
man she's forbidden to. הגמרא gemara says no, we could have learned
out the negative prohibition from another פסוק pasuk of while she's married
to a non-כהן. kohen, לאו, the negative prohibition we learn out from
וכל זר לא יאכל קדש. ve-chol zar lo yochal kodesh.
Any non-כהן kohen. can't eat קדש, kodesh, תרומה. terumah So rather than
learning it just to say the פשט, if you're a non-כהן kohen.
you can't eat תרומה, terumah, we mean if you're connected to a
non-כהן kohen you can't eat תרומה. terumah Okay? And then again, כי
תהיה לאיש זר ki tihye le-ish zar refers to sex with a
man she's forbidden to. So the גמרא Gemara says נפקא, nafka, that's
how we learn it from. So the גמרא Gemara says one minute,
ההוא, hahu, top of סח עמוד ב, samech ches amud beis, ההוא
מבעי ליה, hahu mibayei lei, we need that לגופיה le-gufeih for to
tell you if you're a non-כהן kohen you can't eat תרומה. terumah?
No, תרי וכל זר כתיבי, trei ve-chol zar kesivi, it says twice
וכל זר לא יאכל קדש. ve-chol zar lo yochal kodesh. רש"י Rashi
quotes it. Second line of רש"י Rashi of וכל זר ve-chol zar
of וכל זר לא יאכל קדש ve-chol zar lo yochal kodesh ואלו
גבי בת כהן כתיב ושבה אל בית אביה מלחם אביה תאכל וכל
זר לא יאכל בו. ve-ilu gabei bas kohen kesiv v'shava el beis
aviha mi-lechem aviha tochal ve-chol zar lo yochal bo. Okay? So there's
two וכל זרs. ve-chol zar One is that a non-כהן kohen, can't
eat, and the other is a woman married to a non-כהן kohen,
can't eat. And כי תהיה לאיש זר ki tihye le-ish zar is
about sex with a man she's forbidden to.
Okay, and וכל זר ve-chol zar in all these cases...
exactly. והאי מבעי ליה לדרבי יוסי ברבי חנינא. ve-hai mibayei lei le-de-rabbi
yossi berabi chanina. One minute, we still need כי תהיה לאיש זר
ki tihye le-ish zar not to tell me sex with a man
you're forbidden to, but to tell you what רבי יוסי ברבי חנינא
Rabbi Yossi berabi Chanina says. דאמר רבי יוסי ברבי חנינא de-amar Rabbi
Yossi berabi Chanina וכל זר, ve-chol zar, זרות אמרתי לך ולא אנינות.
zarus amarti lach v'lo aninus. וכל זר לא יאכל בו, ve-chol zar
lo yochal bo, excuse me. Not that it can't tell you, it
can't tell you married to a non-כהן, kohen, it has to tell
you something else. וכל זר, ve-chol zar, זרות אמרתי לך ולא אנינות.
zarus amarti lach v'lo aninus. Only a being a זר zar is
forbidden to eat תרומה, terumah an אונן onen is not. An אונן
onen is forbidden to eat קרבנות korbanos but not forbidden to eat
תרומה. Terumah. So that's what you need it for, not to tell
you married to a כהן. kohen No, רבי יוסי ברבי חנינא מן
וכל וכל זר נפקא. Rabbi Yossi berabi Chanina min ve-chol ve-chol zar
nafka. No, no. That's from the word וכל. ve-chol וכל ve-chol comes
to tell you only about being a זר, zar not about something
else, although normally וכל would seem to be more expansive. And anyway,
זר is coming to tell you married to a non-כהן. kohen So
we have one וכל זר לא יאכל בו ve-chol zar lo yochal
bo to tell you a non-כהן Kohen? can't eat. The other וכל
זר לא יאכל בו, ve-chol zar lo yochal bo, the זר לא
יאכל בו zar lo yochal bo tells you married to a non-כהן
Kohen? you can't eat. And וכל tells you only זר is not
אנינות. aninus. And then we're left with the פסוק pasuk of כי
תהיה לאיש זר ki tihye le-ish zar to tell you that sex
with a man she's forbidden to invalidates her. הגמרא gemara is not
done. והא כתיב מבעי ליה לכדתניא ve-ha kesiv mibayei lei le-chi-de-tanya כשהיא
חוזרת חוזרת לתרומה ואינה חוזרת לחזה ושוק. keshe-hi chozeres chozeres le-terumah ve-einah
chozeres le-chazeh ve-shok. Okay? That when a woman, her husband dies and
she goes back to eating תרומה, Terumah, she goes back to eating
תרומה Terumah. but does not go back to eating קדשים קלים. kodashim
kalim. Which is interesting. ואמר רב מבינא בר רב שילא ve-amar Rav
Mevina bar Rav Shila מאי קרא, mai kra, where do you know
this from? Where's the verse? דכתיב ובת כהן כי תהיה לאיש זר
היא בתרומת הקדשים לא תאכל. de-chesiv u-vas kohen ki tihye le-ish zar
hi bi-sumas ha-kodashim lo tochal. That when she's married to this man
she cannot eat the תרומה, Terumah. but the phrase of תרומה Terumah.
is בתרומת הקדשים. bi-sumas ha-kodashim. And the way we're going to read
it is, לא תאכל במורם מן הקדשים. lo tochal be-muram min ha-kodashim.
בתרומת הקדשים bi-sumas ha-kodashim doesn't mean תרומה, Terumah, it means the חזה
ושוק chazeh ve-shok which is lifted up from קרבנות. korbanos. So once
she was married to a non-כהן, Kohen not during the marriage, during
the marriage she can't eat תרומה Terumah and after she can. But
the other way we're reading the פסוק pasuk is that once she
had been married to him, she can no longer from that point
on, even after he dies, go back to eating the קדשים. kodshim.
So again, it's not telling you sex with a
non-כהן, Kohen? sex with a man she's forbidden to, it's telling you
this special הלכה halacha that she never goes back to eating the
קדשים. kodshim. No, אם כן לכתוב קרא היא בקדשים לא תאכל. im
kein lichtov kra hi be-kodashim lo tochal. Then just if all it
wanted to say was don't eat קדשים kodashim after you've been married
to a non-כהן, Kohen. just say קדשים. kodashim. מאי בתרומת הקדשים? mai
bi-sumas ha-kodashim? Why does it also use the word תרומה? Terumah, שמע
מינה תרתי, shma mina tarti, to tell you both. So it's a
very complicated thing, but the point is we've got enough פסוקים psukim
to tell me a non-כהן Kohen can't eat, married to a non-כהן
Kohen, can't eat, that after her husband dies she goes back to
תרומה Terumah. but she doesn't go back
to
קרבנות. korbanos. for eating תרומה. Terumah, Yes.
Yeah, this this wouldn't be קדשים, Kodashim, because that's only milk but
would this be the מתנת כהנים? Matnat Kohanim? Yes. Okay. Yeah.
Okay. So, right, because obviously she can be שלמים. Shelaimim. Right, this
is something that's specifically right, is eaten by right. Okay, so the
גמרא Gemara says like
this. So, גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay, now, אשכחן כהנת, Ashchan
Kohenet, we find that a כהנת Kohenet becomes invalidated of eating תרומה,
Terumah? but לויה וישראלית מנילן? Leviyah veYisre'elit minayilan? And that's not just
a question of women who are לויה Leviyah and ישראלית, Yisre'elit, it's
a question of the other הלכה. halachah. One הלכה halachah is she
stops eating תרומה. Terumah Fine, you quoted a פסוק pasuk about eating
תרומה. Terumah. How do you know she becomes forbidden to marry a
כהן? Kohen Okay, and that's obviously the much more relevant הלכה halachah
for us nowadays. So that's what's applicable to a לויה וישראלית, Leviyah
veYisre'elit, they never could eat תרומה. Terumah But how do you know
this other הלכה halachah that applies to no matter whether the woman
is a בת כהן Bat Kohen, or לויה וישראלית, Leviyah veYisre'elit, that
she's forbidden to marry a כהן?
kohen, If she has
sex with somebody she's forbidden to. כי דאמר רבי אבא אמר רב,
Ki d'amar Rabbi Abba amar Rav, בת ובת. Bat u'Bat. הכא נמי
בת ובת. Hacha nami Bat u'Bat.
Because the פסוק pasuk says ובת כהן u'Bat Kohen? כי תהיה לאיש
זר, ki tihiyeh l'ish zar. so the extra ו' vav ובת u'Bat
somehow is coming to tell me that not only is this a
הלכה halachah for תרומה, Terumah it's or not only let me say
it this way, not only is it a הלכה halachah for a
בת כהן, bat kohen it's a הלכה halachah for all women. ובת,
u'Bat, all women, even a לויה וישראלית. Leviyah veYisre'elit. Once it's a
הלכה halachah for לויה וישראלית, Leviyah veYisre'elit, the only relevance can't be
a תרומה Terumah. relevance, it has to be a marriage to a
כהן kohen, relevance. So the גמרא Gemara says, כמאן? K'man? כרבי עקיבא
דדרש ווים? K'Rabbi Akiva de'darash vavim? Is this going like רבי עקיבא
Rabbi Akiva that learns out something from an extra ו'? vav? No,
אפילו תימא רבנן, afilu tema Rabbanan, even the רבנן Rabbanan who normally
don't learn out an extra ו'. vav. כולה ובת קרא יתירה הוא.
Kulei u'Bat kra yatera hu. The whole ובת u'Bat is extra, because
it just could have said כי תהיה לאיש זר. Why did it
have to say ובת כהן? u'Bat Kohen? Whose phone is that? Anyway,
why did it have to say ובת כהן? kohen So that whole
thing is extra and therefore that's telling you it applies even to
a non-בת כהן, bat kohen even to ישראלית Yisre'elit and לויה, Leviyah,
and it would apply to לויה וישראלית, Leviyah veYisre'elit, it applies not
only to תרומה, Terumah, but even to marriage. Okay. So now the
גמרא Gemara says like this: אשכחן לתרומה, לכהונה מנלן? Ashchan li'Trumah, li'Kehunah
minayilan?
So we now know that they can't eat תרומה. Terumah, How do
you know they can't marry a כהן? kohen So it says what
I've been telling you. אטו לויה וישראלית לאו לכהונה מרבינן להו? Atu
Leviyah veYisre'elit lav li'Kehunah marbinan lehu? Wait,
I don't understand. When we said it's talking about a ישראלית Yisre'elit
and a לויה, Leviyah, obviously that means for the purpose of not
marrying the כהן. דאי לתרומה, De'ee li'Trumah, because if it was about
not eating תרומה, Terumah what? בנותיהם אכולי תרומה נינהו? Benoteihem echolei Terumah
ninu? Are daughters of their father able to eat תרומה? terumah Right.
A daughter of a non-כהן couldn't eat תרומה terumah? to begin with.
So גמרא Gemara let us see one more line. אלמה לא? Alama
lo? Why not? I can tell you how a ישראלית Yisre'elit could
have eaten תרומה. terumah? משכחת לה דקאכלה בשביל בנה. Mishkachas la de'kachlah
bishvil benah.
Let's say her son was let's say she had been married to
a כהן, she had a son, she was eating תרומה terumah? because
of her son, and now she had sex with this man she's
forbidden to. Right? So there could be a case of that's still
in the world of תרומה terumah? and it's relevant to a ישראלית.
Yisre'elit. She because she has a son with a כהן and because
now she's had this forbidden sex, now she's invalidated. So we're not
yet in the world of marrying כהנים, kohanim maybe we're just still
in the world of תרומה. So the גמרא Gemara says: One minute.
בנה בשביל בנה? Benah bishvil benah?
So the גמרא Gemara says בשביל בנה קל וחומר. bishvil benah kal
va'chomer.
No, I wouldn't need a פסוק to tell me that. That's a
קל וחומר. kal va'chomer. ומה כהנת דבקדושה דנפשה אכלה, u'ma Kohenet de'bikdusha
de'nafsha achlah, a
בת כהנת Bat Kohenet that could eat on her own account, פסלה,
this act of sex invalidates her. לויה וישראלית דלא אכלה אלא בשביל
בנה, Leviyah veYisre'elit de'lo achlah ela bishvil benah, this case where she's
only eating because of her child, לא כל שכן, lo kol sheken,
of course sex would invalidate her of course forbidden sex would invalidate
her.
גמרא says what?
That if a בת כהנת Bat Kohenet who is basically entitled on
her own account to eat, forbidden sex invalidates her for eating תרומה,
a בת ישראל Bat Yisrael who only eats because of her child,
how much more so should this act invalidate. So the גמרא says:
No, that's not a
קל וחומר. kal va'chomer. היא הנותנת, Hee hanotenet, that it makes a
lot of sense. כהנת דקדיש גופה, Kohenet de'kadish gufah, a בת כהנת
Bat Kohenet that's eating because of her personal status, then פסלה, sex
under you know you know impinges on her personal status and invalidates
her. הא דלא קדיש גופה, Ha de'lo kadish gufah, she's
not doesn't have קדושה, kedushah, it's not her status that entitles her
to eat, it's her child that entitles her to eat. So maybe
her status doesn't matter. Maybe her status is irrelevant. If she's a
ישראלית Yisre'elit and she can eat, maybe even if she had forbidden
sex she can eat, it's not about her status. לא לא פסלה.
Lo lo paslah. So therefore, so we're going to end with this
question. So now we've said we've included ישראלית כהנת כהנת ישראלית ולויה,
Yisre'elit Kohenet Kohenet Yisre'elit veLeviyah, that the forbidden sex invalidates them from
eating תרומה, and you need to include even ישראלית ולויה Yisre'elit veLeviyah
that they can't eat תרומה in the case that they have a
child. So we've totally said all women, forbidden sex gets them out
of the תרומה category. What we're going to turn back to turn
to tomorrow is how do you know that it invalidates them from
marrying a כהן, which is what's really relevant for us today, okay?
And look at that, we pretty much I would say we caught
up.
Yes.
I was wrong about miscarriage rates. They're high enough that the percentage
increased.
I would have imagined that. I would have imagined that.
So if you're a כהן, right, and you have guests, can you
feed them תרומה? Especially for שבועות Shavuos meal. If you're what? Feed
your כהנים kohanim guests תרומה? כהנים kohanim guests תרומה?
Only כהנים guests? How could you feed a non-כהן guest תרומה? You're
מאכיל ma'achil somebody something טריפה. treife.
Even if this is your daughter who's now married to a ישראל,
Yisrael she just comes home for like a meal.
Yeah, no, she
still can't eat it because she's completely out of her father's house.
Exactly. It's not the physical house, it's the household.
Right, so even though like, you know,
she's coming home and there's no like temporary exceptions for like, you
know, if she comes home for like a meal. No. Right, there's
no temporary exceptions for like if you come
home for like a meal. To talk about a בת כהן bat
kohen having קדושת הגוף? kedushas haguf?
Yeah, she loses it when she gets married. So what kind of...
Yeah, but then she reverts to... But first of all, does she
lose... I mean the whole idea is, right, is it that she
has קדושת הגוף kedushas haguf or is it that she's connected to...
Right. She's קדושת הגוף, kedushas haguf, right, she loses it when...
Well, yeah, I don't know if you would say that she loses
it or that her... I mean look, you're right in general to
think about her as קדושת הגוף kedushas haguf rather than to think
about her as, you know, that's the question. In a way it's
reflected in the language. Does the גמרא refer to it as בת
כהן or as כהנת, kohenes, right? You know, בת כהן means yes,
she has real status but because she's connected the same way her
slaves eat and wife eats, so the daughter of a כהן eats
too. Right. You're saying כהנת kohenes and speaking about קדושת הגוף kedushas
haguf thinks about it in a different way. You're right and in
fact he somehow saying that even though she has this קדושת הגוף,
kedushas haguf, I don't know if you would say marriage to ישראל
Yisrael removes the קדושה kedusha or just, you know, sort of says
even though she has the קדושה kedusha she's not eating because of
her connection to the ישראל household. So Dov, you missed the initial
request which is I'm away Friday, שבת, Shabbos, Sunday. So Michael took
Friday. Any possibility you could take שבת Shabbos or Sunday?
Right. I can take Sunday, that's fine. Okay. Great. שבת... Shabbos...
Any students around?
So I'll ask, yeah, I'll ask one of my students. So we
got Friday and Sunday covered, I will see about, I'll see about
getting שבת Shabbos covered.
Oh, that was my problem.